So which plan is better Bajaj My Health
Care Plan and ICICI Lamb Elovate Now
Elovate plan is back by one of the
largest private banks in India
ICICI Bank Bajaj is back by the largest
NBFC in the country but brand aside
what really matters is to understand the
fine print in the core offerings and even more how is their
claims and service track
record and that is what we will be covering
in this video using my 20 years of
experience and deep data back research
from ILM Research I will break down
both these plans clearly for everything that matters.
[Music]
Mahavir Chopra The Founder and Chief
Executive Officer of Beshq.org.
[Music]
So here is what we'll be covering in this
video.  One a comparison of unique features
with the fine print.  To a quick roll call of
the core benefits, the waiting periods and the
fine print.  Three: A detailed look at the
real-world service experience,
starting with customer service and
mostly claims experience.  Then a
quick comparison of the prying and finally we will
understand how these plans are
rated by ILM Research.  India's only
independent insurance ratings that through
deep research gives one single data back
rating for all insurance plans making
it easier to compare all products in the
market.  One Thing Before We Move Ahead in the
video.  Look, health insurance is full of
terms and conditions, legal and medical jar.
Well I try to keep it easy for you to
understand at any point if you feel
confused and overwhelmed and want to have a
personalized one to one consultation with
industry experts.  You can always consult
India's top five experts only
on course.g completely for free.
Mind you these experts are not call center
freshers.  These are experts with real
experience.  Ok.  So moving on to the
USpiece.  First we will take the USP of
ICICI Lamb Elevate which are unique and
then we will move to the comparable USP of
both the plans.  Ah there are two important
USPs in ICI lobbyd that do not
exist in Bajaj My Health Care.  One is
unlimited sum insured.  So ICICI Lombard
offers an option of unlimited sum assured
when you choose the sum assured option.  So like there is
sum insured of Rs 7.5 lakh, sum insured of Rs 10 lakh
, sum insured of Rs 15 lakh.  You
can also choose the option of unlimited sum insured from the buttons where you choose sum insured.  This is not available in Bajaj.
Next is Infinite Care.
For instance, if you do
not want unlimited sum insured or you
feel its premium is too high then you can choose something called
Infinite Care.  In that what
happens is that is an unlimited sum
insured but just one time in your life time
in your family's life time.  Whatever
policy you are taking,
you can claim unlimited sum insured once in the lifetime of the policy.
Whether your claim is of Rs 5 crore
, Rs 10 crore, Rs 15 crore, no matter how much the
insurance company is saying, you
can make unlimited claim once.  This
is a very important feature.  Because when we
choose the sum insured, we always think in the back of
the mind that how much sum insured
is enough.  If medical science has made a lot of
progress, then of late the
hospitalization cost has increased a lot or
such diseases have come up where the expenses are very
high.  So we don't know, this is really really
helpful for that.
Now moving on to the other USPs which are
comparable between both these plans.  Now
Normally in case of ICICI Lobbed Elevate you
get a bonus of 20%.  It is not linked to
basically claims it's called a liability
bonus.  And your total reaches 100%.
But if you take an add-on, a very
interesting change happens.  100% No
Claim Not No Claim 100% Loyalty Bonus
every year and accumulates unlimited
times.  Meaning,
your sum insured will keep increasing, keep
increasing, keep increasing, as per the number of years you are taking it.  Now
moving on to Bajaj.  There is basically nothing like this in Bajaj.
You are getting no claim bonus.  There
is no loyalty bonus in this.  If your
sum insured is above Rs 5 lakh, you will get 50%
no claim bonus and it will go up to a maximum of 100%.
This is a link to claims like I
already mentioned.  Moving on to another
benefit in both these plus that
exist is called the maternity benefit.
Now in case of long maternity is covered but it
is covered through an add on.  It is not
directly covered.  It gives you a sum
insured of 10% of your SI.  So whatever
sum insured you have taken.  Suppose
you have taken a sum insured of Rs. 1 lakh.  You have
sum insured for Rs 1 crore.  That's 10% of it.  But there
is a cap.  The cap is 1 lakh.  You
cannot claim more than Rs 1 lakh.  There
is a waiting period of 2 years in this.  This is an add on like
I told you.  Now the maternity cover in Bajaj is
inbuilt.  You do
not have to pay any extra premium.  It's part of
the plan.  It is available for SI above Rs 5
lakh.  Now what is the sum insured that is
available?
Maternity is always insured separately.  So you can cover Rs 500 to Rs 1 lakh
depending on your sum insured.
For example, for Rs 10 lakh you will
get Rs 500.  If you are taking a base cover of Rs 20 lakh,
you will get up to Rs 1 lakh.  The
waiting period in this is
three years.  The one we saw in ICICI had a
waiting period of two years.  The
waiting period in this is 3 years.  Moving on to
newborn coverage.  Right?  So
what is newborn coverage? As soon as the maternity
coverage is approved, we will talk about the cover that is provided to the baby when it is born.
So in case of IC
Lomard it is available again it is an add on in this
newborn babies are covered up to 90
days whatever maternity sum insured
you have taken, you will basically get its 2X cover
for baby cover.  Right?  The
waiting period for A2Y will obviously be applicable
as it is linked to maternity.  Now
Moving On To Bajaj, how is baby covered
?  So like maternity is an
inbuilt benefit in Bajaj.  Baby cover is also an
inbuilt benefit.  It is a separate cover. It is
sum insured from Rs 1 lakh to Rs 15 lakh depending
on your sum insured.
For example, if you have taken health insurance of Rs 10 lakh, then the
baby is covered for Rs 5 lakh.  This is a
very good honestly inbuilt benefit
for people who are young couples.  Nowadays it is being
seen that baby bonds are
a bit unstable and their cost is
very expensive.  So
having a zero day baby cover is in my view
invaluable for young couples.  So do look at it if
you are specifically a young couple.  Now
Moving On To OPD S N Benefit.  OPD is an
add-on to ICICI LBAD.  If you
see, the difference between ICICI Lambard and Bajaj is that in
a way it is basically a buffet,
ICICI and Bajaj is like a thali where you have given everything
pre-packaged,
in case of Bajaj, everything that we are speaking about till now whatever we
spoke about, all of them are
add ons.  So you have to choose
everything.  So when you buy ICICI, it
is very important to have an expert with you
because how do you have to choose?  You have so
many benefits that it can be difficult to choose.
So do try to use an
expert when you are basically trying to buy
ICICI LBA plan from here.  So let us
quickly see what ICICI LB looks for in OPD plans.  And it is an
add on like I
already said it basically allows you to cover physical
consultation, study consultation, diagnostic
pharmacy, all which is a complete array of all
OPD expenses.
SI options are 5000 10000 15000 20000
25000 which you can choose.  The
important thing to understand in this is that
only cashless is available.  So you will have to
download their app and then
opt for it.  Maybe you could have done it through their call centre
also but you have to do it through them only.
You cannot do it directly.
Moving on to Bajaj again like I said
Bajaj has inbuilt OPD.  In this you have
physical consultation as well as teleconsultation.  There
is consultation and there is test.  There
is no mention of pharmacy anywhere in this.  Is
What I Saw.  The coverage you get in this is
2x of your base premium.  So,
whatever health insurance premium you are paying,
2x of it, if you have
paid a premium of Rs 20,000, then you are
getting an inbuilt OPD cover of Rs 400.
Basically, one of the most important things in this is that you have to do it after
taking pre-approval.  Whether you go
cashless or reimburse.  If you
do it without pre-approval, there may be an
OP of 20%.  But the interesting
thing was that it is inbuilt in it and
in its case you have to acquire and customize it.
Ok?  The next benefit that I want to
compare your quickly which is a
USB is world wide.  The
interesting thing in World Wide's case is that both
created add-ons.  This is very actually
reasonable because not everybody would need a
cover for let's say treatment outside
India.  Now in case of ICICI Almard
both emergency and plan treatments are
covered.  Up to sum insured is covered.
Cashless only available.  So if you
want to go for reimbursement, you cannot do it.  It
feels great to hear
that cashless only is available.  It's a good
thing.  I will not have to pay any money.
But the important thing to understand is that
if you have to take reimbursement and you do
not get the network hospital of ICICI Lambdar
when you are outside, then you will not
get the claim for it.  You have to get treatment only by going to the cashless network.  If
ever such a
situation arises where the hospital
is not available then it is not going to get
covered.  Very very difficult to understand this.   There
is a two year waiting period.  You because
plan treatment is covered in it.  So it is reasonable that there will be a
waiting period of 2 years.  Immediate
cover will not be available.  In the case of Bajaj again, this is the
only important add-on that
we are comparing.  Everything else that I
told you was inbuilt, mostly
only emergency cover is there in it.  Plan
treatment is not covered in this.  Meaning if someone gets
cancer and goes outside for treatment,
it will not be covered.  Emergency
means if there is an accident or some sudden
illness and you are outside then that will be covered
in this.  Up to SI is covered.  10%
copay will be applicable for all claims.  There is one more
thing in this which is important to understand.
Your trips
cannot be more than 45 days.  And the total of all
trips put together cannot exceed 180 days.
That is the world wide cover.  Ok?
Now we'll do a quick roll call of the core
benefits in the plan.  These core benefits are
numerous.  Because of this your
majority part of Azar Hospital will get
paid.  So the first one is room rent.
In case of room rent, ICIC Along
gives you a single private room by default.  You will
get a single private AC room.  But if you
want any kind of freedom to
choose any type of room, then
you will have to pay additional premium.  One add
on is to get one and there you will be that in any room.
Bajaj also offers only single private AC room.
But in case of sum insured of
15 la and above it allows you to
convert it into any room through an add on.
Now Moving On To Pre & Post
Hospitalization Pre & Post 90 Days 180
Days In Case Of ICICI 60 Days & 90 Days In
Case Of Bajaj Aleas.  Day care treatments
all treatments covered in both Bajaj and
ICICI In domiciliary treatment 17
exclusions have been put by ICICI and 16
exclusions have been put by Bajaj but
domiciliary treatment is covered so typically
asthma, diabetes, hypertension are
not covered and rest all the
things will be
covered in domiciliary hospitalization both modern treatment and organ donor without any
limits both the plans are
covering now moving on to the good to have
benefits there are two important good to have
benefits one is consumable cover in case
of ICI same card again this is an add on.
You have to choose it by paying additional premium.
In this you will get 68 listed non-
medical items covered.  In case of
Bajaj it is inbuilt.  Like I said, it has a
lot of things built into it.  There is one more thing which is
inbuilt.  105 non-medical items are
covered here up to SI.  Next is
Restoration Benefit.  In case of ICICI it
is inbuilt.  You can restore unlimited times.
It is applicable for all instances
even for partial exhaustion and it triggers
from the second clear.  In case of Bajaj the
Restoration Again is inbuilt unlimited for
sum insured above 5 lakh. If your sum
insured is below 5 lakh then it will be done only
once and if it is above 5 lakh then it will be unlimited.
All analysis but
you can use it only in full exhaustion, you
cannot use it in partial exhaustion,
this can be a little problem. If multiple
claims come then Restoration
has a little less better feature as compared to ICICI LA Again.
You can use it for second claim.  Moving
on to the waiting periods.  The standard 30-day waiting
period
is applicable for both policies.  Whenever you buy the policy,
only sickness claims are not payable in the first 30 days.
Only
accident claims are payable.  This
is normal.  Everything happens in policies.
Next is the PED waiting period of 36 months, which
is standard in both cases.
As per IRDA.  You can reduce this to 12 or 24 minutes by
paying an additional premium.
Both in Bajaj and ICICI in LBR.
Now there is one more customization that ICICI
LBA offers in case of pre-existing
disease cover.  So basically what these people
call it is jump start rider.
In this, you
can further reduce the waiting period for around six diseases.  You
can do it for only 30 days.  What disease is this?   If you have
asthma, diabetes, BP,
cholesterol, obesity and if
you have undergone angioplasty more than a year ago, then
you can get cover within 30 days.
You have to apply.  The insurance
company will charge extra premium and
after that you will get this cover.  Now moving to the
specified treatment waiting period which is a
list of options, treatments.
An insurance company
covers you only after 2 years when you first
buy the policy.  There is a waiting period of 24 months in both.
As per standard IDA.  In both cases, you can extend it to 12 months by paying
additional premium.  Well,
one thing I wanted to tell you was that when I was
recording this video, the research
team raised their hands and told me, so it is important that I
tell you that in case of certain
treatments like non-PD cases,
hypertension, diabetes and cardiac
conditions, if you do not have PD and if you get it
in the first 90 days, then there will be a waiting
period for it.  Ok?  So if there is PD then there will be a
waiting period of 3 years.  If there is no PD then
in the first 30 90 days not in 30 days.  If
you suffer from any type of illness due to these three diseases or
you undergo any
type of hospitalization, then it will
not be covered.  It was important.  Thank you research
team.  Moving on to customer service.
In customer service, ICICI LBA toll free number
is showing average and in case of Twitter, it is showing
slow.  It is slow.  This means that if
you complain on Twitter, you will get a
slow response.  Bajaj is the slower of the two.
So, in the audits we conducted, our service to you is
not appearing to be that
great.  The next one we go to is we
go to Claims Experience.  This
is the main part of this video.  There are four
specific ratios that we will discuss.
Now the first ratio is the speed of
claim settlement which is basically the
total claims that an insurance
company has.  How many claims does it settle in the first 30 days?
This lets you know
how fast an insurance company is
in claim settlement.  In case of ICICI it is 99.94.
In case of Bajaj it is 99.4.  Both are equally
good.  Meaning, there is nothing much in it, neither
green flag nor red flag.
Both are good.  Ok?  A second is
claim complaints.  In case of claim complaints
tally over ICI is 144% in case of Bajaj it is
0.03% I think this would be the best in the
industry one of the best in the industry
in terms of complaints.  I don't think I have ever seen
a number as low as this, but
interestingly, at least in my memory, this is a
very good number.  A moving on
to incurred claims ratio.  Inc. Claim Ratio
is a ratio where you find out how much premium an insurance company
collects and
how much it pays in claims.
In case of ICI SEM,
this ratio is 85.53% which is ₹100 if claim is
₹100 then ICI
pays 85.53 in the same claim.  In case of
Bajaj it is 90.01% now
both actually fail in our benchmark.
We say as a company that 60
to 80% ICR should be yours.  If it
is below 60% then it means that an insurance
company is paying very few claims.  It is
cutting the claims a lot and if it is above 80%
then it is doing it on a lot of claims.  Something
is wrong and the premiums will increase in future because the
insurance company is not
making profits.  The ratio of both is bad.
85.53% 90.01% But of course between the two,
Bajaj is the worst.  Right?  Now
moving on to rejection ratio.
I follow this ratio a lot.  I think
this ratio is very important to understand.  How
an insurance company is dealing with
claims.  Rejection is obviously the
most important parameter that I feel and that is why
I look at it.  So let's see what the
ratios are.  In case of ICICI the rejection
ratio is 14.11% which is quite high.  Of all the
reviews I've done so far,
I think there are only one or two companies that
come close to this.  Bajaj which is 5.68%.
5.68% is also high compared to some plans
that I have seen.  But in case of both these
plans when you compare ICI has a very
bad ratio at least the claim rejection
ratio compared to Bajaj.  Right?  Is where they don't
fare that well.  They are rejecting more
claims than the standard what I have
seen.  Moving on to the prying of both the
plies.  We have seen all this,
what is the track record of a human company?
What is USPS?  We also looked at
who is better in core benefits?  who's bad?
How much does the premium charge?  There is a lot to
know.  So the premium of ICICI LAD
here is the standard one that we take for
Mr. Kumar, 30 years old with wife who is also
probably 30 years old.  One kid one
year old Mumbai based 10 lakh sum insured.
₹13,964
in case of ICICI Elevate in case of Bajaj
is ₹366
right in ICICI, all the add ons that I told
you have to be taken separately, hence the
premium will appear a little less because you have to
choose.  Bajaj has baked in a lot.
Right?  So because of that the premium
is a little different.  But obviously what I am
saying here is I am not trying to
justify the premiums of any of these two
pluses.  I am just trying to give you an
understanding of why there is such a big difference.  The
important thing will be
what is suitable for you and what is not.
For that, my suggestion will always be that
you should take personalized consultation.
Whoever is a good expert around you
whose name is for claims not for
sales.  You will find many people sticking to the policy.
Who
is famous for claims?  Find a person like that.
Buy the policy from him because he will give you the right guidance.  I will
find the right side plan for you.
If you are not able to find any such
consultant expert in your area then
you should definitely come here.  Here, we have
brought together the top 5% insurance experts of India so that
customers can get free consultation
and right guidance.  Moving on to
ILM ratings.  This is a very critical
part of this video.  In this I will
tell you how ILM, an independent
research company, has rated the
plans.  This is a lot of things.  Because
we are all watching everything.  Looking at the product
, looking at the claims, looking at the service
, looking at the price.  It becomes
very difficult for us to understand how all these plans
rank compared to each other.
Right?  We've seen a lot of ratios, but
how do we look at these plans when we have to compare them?
A rating is one way to do it, which is a
very recognized thing worldwide
that ILM brings.  ILM does not
charge any commissions and any marketing fees
from any insurance companies and that is why it
is completely
independent.  We can trust them.   That's why
we have included them here
in this video.  Ah product benefits
4.69 out of five is what ICICI gets.
3.47 out of five in the case of Bajaj.  That is
the rating that gets.  So ICIC is fairing well
in case of product.  Now moving
on to customer service 4.14 in case of ICIC
4.19 in case of Bajaj equally good
both in terms of customer service.  Claims
experience: 4.27 in case of ICICI, 4.64
in case of Bajaj.  So Bajaj fares better in
claims and ICICI fares better in
product.  Now, based on the mixture and
blend of all this,
ILM gives a standard overall rating.   Let me
tell you that.  4.32 in case of ICICI
LBR and 3.93 in case of Bajaj.  So on
IL&FS ratings basically ICICI LBA Elevate
is rated higher compare to Bajaj My
Healthcare.  That's the video.  Hope you liked the
comparison and the analysis that we did.
We tried to give you guidance
if you were comparing these two plans. Hope
your doubts got cleared.  If any doubt is
not cleared then as I
told you earlier, talk to an expert.  Do
n't talk to any call center person who
joins two-three months before the deadline and will read out a couple of
scripts to you.  Experts are those
who have seen claims,
who have seen everything in the world, how
you know insurance companies behave, when
times are bad, when we are in the hospital, then
talk to the expert accordingly,
of course you can get a free consultation from the expert, the
link pin is in the comment as well as
in the description and I am
giving a number here, you
can send hi on that number through WhatsApp and
as soon as you send hi from that, someone from our team can
call and book a consultation for you.
Hope you like the video.  If you
like the video do subscribe to our channel and
press like.  We feel very happy.  We
sit here and feel a little rejoiced that
since we have worked so hard, we should at least get some
encouragement.  Thank you very much.